Carl Moon photograph collection, circa. 1903-1914
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Carl Moon Photograph Collection, circa. 1903-1914
MS 285
Moon, Carl, 1878-1948
The Carl Moon collection is comprised of photographs, ca. 1903-1914, consisting of black and white copy prints of Apache, Hopi, Navajo, and other American Indians. The collection is artificially arranged into seven series: Portraits, Cafts, Music, Men, Habitat, Ceremonies and Family. Printed on fiber paper 5 by 8 inches or smaller, these photographs are annotated with names and places, and some are dated. The bulk of the images consist of portraits of individuals, groups, and ceremonies.
.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born in Wilmington, Ohio, Carl E. Moon learned his craft as an apprentice to a photography studio. He moved to Albuquerque, New Mexico, opened his own studio, and made pictorial studies of Indians in the region. Between 1907 to 1914, he worked for Fred Harvey in a studio at El Tovar, Grand Canyon, Arizona. He established a studio in Pasadena, California, where he continued to photograph and paint. During the last three decades of this career, Moon produced works for Henry E. Huntington, published Indians of the Southwest, and contributed illustrations for children's books written by his wife, Grace Purdie Moon.
Organization
This collection is organized into seven series:
Series I: Portraits, circa. 1903-1914
Series II: Crafts, circa. 1905-1907
Series III: Music, circa. 1906
Series IV: Men, circa. 1904-1914
Series V: Habitat, circa. 1904-1914
Series VI: Ceremonies, circa. 1904-1914
Series VII: Family, circa. 1905-1914
Scope and Content Note
Photographs, ca. 1903-1914, consisting of black and white copy prints of Apache, Hopi, Navajo, and other American Indians. The collection is artificially arranged into seven series: Portraits, Cafts, Music, Men, Habitat, Ceremonies and Family. Printed on fiber paper 5 by 8 inches or smaller, these photographs are annotated with names and places, and some are dated. The bulk of the images consist of portraits of individuals, groups, and ceremonies.
Access Terms
Moon, Carl, 1878-1948 -- Photograph collections
Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Portraits
Indians of North America -- Southwest, New -- Rites and ceremonies
Hopi Indians -- Pictorial works
Navajo Indians -- Pictorial works
Apache Indians -- Pictorial works
Osage Indians -- Pictorial works
Taos Indians -- Pictorial works
Pueblo Indians -- Pictorial works
Photographs
Container List
- Series I: Portraits (First 11 are Navajo), circa. 1903-1914
  - Psoothlanny, Pso-tianny. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yah-otza-begey, Ya-ohtse-begay. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Little Navajo Girl, Ose-pah. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Little Navajo Girl, Ose-pah, (side view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tlizzy-Talany, Navajo Patriarch, (side view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tlizzy-Talany, Navajo Patriarch, (front view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tlizzy-Talany, Navajo Patriarch, (three quarter front view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Do-bazin, (profile). 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Do-bazin, (front view). 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cho'-bah-begey or The Wolf. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Navajo Chief, Vicente. 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Azi, Osage. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bro-ki-he-kah, Osage. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Peh-tsa-moie, Osage. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bare Legs, Osage. 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mo-cha-tah, Osage girl. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Na-dez-pah, Little Navajo Girl. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Young Navajo girl about ten, no name given. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Santiago, Santo Domingo man. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Zuni Governor. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Last of his people. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Do-Gow, the half breed, half white mountain Apache half Mexican. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Do-Gow, the half breed, half white mountain Apache half Mexican, with hat on. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Juan Pacheko, San Felipi Man. 1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hopi Girl, Ko-mah-pua-ee. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hopi Girl, Ko-mah-pua-ee, (side view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ka-yat-te-di, Laguna girl. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hostin Nez. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pedro Cayete, Santa Clara governor. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Isleta Maiden Water Carrier, Marie Chi-wi-we. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Warrior. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ahs-lah-ko, Jicarrilla Apache (side view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ahs-lah-ko, Jicarrilla Apache, (front view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Venturo of Taos. 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Venturo of Taos, (facing right). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Standing Elk (looks same as Venturo), (side view). 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Standing Elk (looks same as Venturo), with War bonnet on (three quarter view). 1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Conjurere, Taos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gray Hawk, Taos. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clau-Palie, Taos, Buffalo headpiece. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clau-Palie, Taos, Buffalo headpiece. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Geronimo Gomez, Taos. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Geronimo Gomez, Taos, (side view). 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gray Hawk, Taos, (side view). 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Juan Concho, Taos, (left profile). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Juan Concho, Taos, (frontal view face, body faces right). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Juan Concho, Taos, (frontal view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jim Little Feather, (left profile). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jim Little Feather, (front view). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wild Flower, Albida, (full length). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Albida, (sitting, partial left). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Warrior's Bride or Chief's Bride, Albida. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sunlight and Shadow, Taos mother. No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wild Flower, Albida, (full length). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wild Flower, Albida, (holding basket plants, standing). No Date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Crafts, circa. 1905-1907
  - Hopi Weaver, village of Tewa. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Isletta Pottery Maker, Marie Chi-Wee-Wee. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Grinding Corn, Olha-Chi-De, Walpi, Acoma. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mending Arrows, Francisco, the arrow maker. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Taos Moccasin Maker. No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Primitive Art, painting bearskin (crouched position). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Primitive Art, painting bearskin (standing, left hand on top of skin). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Primitive Are, painting bearskin (both hands holding top of skin). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Navajo Weaver, woman, Canyon de Chelley (facing right). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Navajo Weaver, woman, Canyon de Chelley (facing left). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Navajo Weaver, woman, Canyon de Chelley, small child at left (facing right). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Nampeyo, Hopi pottery maker (facing right). 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Nampeyo, Hopi pottery maker (facing left). 1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Taos Arrowmaker, holding arrow (large print). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Taos Arrowmaker, looking down at arrow (large print). No Date (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III: Music, circa. 1906
  - Flute Player, Cha-donnie-doh, (legs bent). No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Flute Player, Cha-donnie-doh, (legs stretched). No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lone Singer, also Cha-donnie-doh. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Dancing Lesson, Taos. 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The CornSong, Jeronimo Gomez. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Love Song, Taos, Jeronimo Gomez. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Village Drummer of San Juan. No Date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series IV: Men, circa. 1904-1914
  - In Ambush or The Last Arrow, Jeronimo Gomez. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Acoma Trail. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Return of the Harvesters, Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Night Riders. No date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Runner, Taos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Hunter. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Open Country, Taos Indians. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Hunter on the Hill, Taos, (facing left, coming up hill). No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Hunter on the Hill, Taos, (facing right, going down hill). No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Scout. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reflections, Taos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series V: Habitat, circa. 1904-1914
  - Hopi Door Steps, Mo-hi-qui-lio, (facing right). 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hopi Door Steps, Mo-hi-qui-lio, (facing front). 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hopi Villages in the Second Mesa. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Hopi House, First Mesa, Walpi, Witch House. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ancient Hopi House, First Mesa, Walpi, Witch House, (burro or horse in front). No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Snake Kiva, Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Entrance to Kiva, Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Zuni Buildings. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Zuni Baking Ovens. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ovens in Acoma. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Taos Village, (trees on left). No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Taos Village, (animals in front, houses in back). No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Walpi, Hopi Village. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Return of the Harvesters, Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Return of the Harvesters, Walpi, Oraibi family coming home from their fields, (burro in foreground coming toward camera). No Date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Ceremonies, circa. 1904-1914
  - The Medicine Man, unusual picture, Indian objects (patient seated). No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Medicine Man, unusual picture, Indian objects (patient standing). No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Vow. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tablita Dance at Acoma. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Santo Domingo Dancers, Santo Domingo Pueblo, during corn dance. 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chief Koy-yahwa-meh, Chief of Hopi snake priests in dance costume; he is chief of All Walpi snake dancers. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sacred Water Bowl, also is Koy-yahwa-mah. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hopi Snake Dancer, Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hopi Snake Dance, village at Shipaulovi. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Going up the Mesa Trail, Hopi snake dancers, Walpi. 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Taos Medicine Man or Through the Sage, Juan Concho. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Medicine Drum. No Date (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Family, circa. 1905-1914
  - The Story Teller, Taos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Their First Born, Taos. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Off to the River, Taos, Crucita and little boy. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Their Rondezvous, Jim and Alvida. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Apache Mother and Child, White RIver Reservation. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Navajo Mother and Child. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Mother and Child (standing in doorway, blanket about baby). No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Orabi; Mother and Children, Hopi. 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Homeward Bound, Hopi Women of Second Mesa. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Sisters, Orabi (boy in background). 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Sisters, Orabi, figures in center of picture (facing camera). 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Mother and Child, baby on mothers back (standing). No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Mother and Child, Shipaulovi, means place of the peaches (sitting on steps, baby on side in blanket). 1914 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hopi Mirror, the pool at Walpi. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Santa Clara Maiden, Rosa Pah-ee-la-tah (Po-ee-lata). No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Voice of the Stream, Taos woman by River in Shunta Canyon. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Apache Land, White Mountain Apache. No Date (Box 1, Folder 7)